<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide link="/doc/desktop.html">
<title>Gentoo Linux Desktop Configuration Guide</title>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant Goodyear</mail></author>

<abstract>
   This guide shows you configure Gentoo Linux to be a full-purpose
   desktop system.  Specifically, we walk through installing and 
   configuring X, KDE, OSS and alsa (sound), postfix (electronic mail), 
   cups (printing),
   and samba (unix/windows interoperability).
</abstract>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>22 June 2001</date>

<chapter>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Needless to say, you first need to have Gentoo Linux installed
(<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/doc/install.html</uri>).  Having finished
that rather enjoyable process, you also need to download the <e>Portage</e>
tree.  You really should read the Portage User Guide 
(<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/doc/portage-user.html</uri>), but if you're
in a hurry you just need to type:
</p>
<pre># <i>emerge rsync</i></pre>
<p>A quick note is in order about the packages that I have chosen to 
discuss here.  Gentoo Linux has a considerable wealth of window managers,
mail transport agents, etcetera that can easily be installed.  The specific
packages that I have chosen to cover are not preferred by Gentoo Linux, they
are simply packages that the author likes and/or knows how to configure.
In other words, they're the packages on the author's own desktop.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>X and KDE</title>

<section>
<title>Installation</title>
<body>
<p>
Having installed Gentoo Linux and updated Portage, 
my first task is generally to install X
and KDE.  X takes forever to compile, and KDE takes even longer,
so I highly recommend doing this right before going to bed.
</p>
<p>
It's always useful to use the <c>--pretend</c> flag before doing
an <c>emerge</c> to see what dependencies are going to be installed, and in our
case it's quite a lot.
</p>
<pre>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/kde-base/kdebase</i>
# <i>emerge --pretend kdebase-2.1.1-r1.ebuild</i>

These are the packages that I would merge, in order.

Calculating dependencies............... done!
[ebuild N  ] media-sound/cdparanoia-3.9.8 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/jpeg-6b-r2 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/tiff-3.5.6_beta to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-base/xfree-4.1.0 to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-libs/openmotif-2.1.30-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/alsa-lib-0.5.10-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/mesa-glu-3.4.2 to /
[ebuild N  ] kde-base/kde-env-2.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/lcms-1.06 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/libmng-1.0.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/audiofile-0.2.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/libpng-1.0.11 to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-libs/qt-x11-2.3.0 to /
[ebuild N  ] app-text/sgml-common-0.6.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] kde-base/kdelibs-2.1.2 to /
[ebuild N  ] kde-base/kdebase-2.1.1-r1 to /

# <i>emerge kdebase-2.1.1-r1.ebuild</i>
</pre>
<p>Have a nice nap!</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Configuring</title>
<body>
<p>
I like using the console-based <c>xf86config</c> program to configure X.
Before you start, you'll need to know the horizontal and vertical refresh
rates of your monitor (my viewsonic G773 has Horizontal: 30-69 KHz, 
Vertical: 55-90 KHz), the type and amount of ram (in KB) of your video card
(a 32768 KB GeForce card, in my case), and the type and device of your
mouse (an intellimouse plugged into the ps/2 port <path>/dev/psaux</path>).
</p>
<pre># <c>xf86config</c></pre>
<figure link="/images/XF86config.png" short="xf86config image"/>
<p>Because I have a three-button mouse I choose not to enable 
3-button emulation.  I don't add any additional XKB keyboard options
because I don't know what any of them do.  You'll have to guess at
a screen resolution and pixel depth that you'll like.  I happen
to like 1280x1024 at 24bpp on my viewsonic, but that's only because it
doesn't work at a higher resolution.  If you've never done this before,
don't be surprised if you end up running <c>xf86config</c> multiple
times.</p>

<note>If you don't know the refresh rates of your monitor, try doing a 
google search, <uri>http://www.google.com</uri>, on the model number and
manufacturer of your monitor.  The refresh rates are generally given as
part of the monitor specs.</note>

<warn>If you're an X-configuring veteran, you may be used to making
a symbolic link from your mouse device to <path>/dev/mouse</path>.  If
you are using <c>devfs</c> you may be unpleasantly surprised to discover
that your link is not preserved upon rebooting.</warn>

<pre># <i>startx</i></pre>
<p>If you configured X properly, running <c>startx</c> should start an
amazingly ugly X window manager (twm, to be specific).  If X comes up,
you're good to go.  Hit <c>&lt;ctrl&gt;&lt;alt&gt;&lt;backspace&gt;</c>
to kill the X server.</p>

<p>If you have a wheel mouse you'll want to edit the XF86Config file
by hand:</p>
<pre>
# <i>cp /etc/X11/XF86Config /etc/X11/XF86Config.working</i>
# <i>vim /etc/X11/XF86Config</i></pre>
<figure link="/images/XF86Configalt.png" short="XF86Config file"/>
<p>Because I have an intellimouse I changed the "Protocol" from 
"PS/2" to "IMPS/2".  Getting the wheel to scroll just requires
adding the 'Option "ZAxisMapping" "4 5"' line, where '4' and '5'
correspond to mouse wheel up and mouse wheel down.
</p>
<note>Netscape 4.x won't scroll with the wheel by default; you'll need
to create an .Xdefaults file first.  See 
<uri>http://www-sop.inria.fr/koala/colas/mouse-wheel-scroll/</uri>
for instructions.  Better yet, use <c>konqueror</c>, <c>opera</c>,
<c>mozilla</c>, <c>galeon</c>, or some other real browser.</note>

<p>Run <c>startx</c> again just to make sure that X still comes up.
Assuming that it does, kill X and we'll start a real window manager
instead.  First, though, we need to fix a minor KDE bug.
</p>
<pre># <i>vim /opt/kde2.1/bin/startkde</i></pre>
<pre caption="the top of the startkde file after it has been fixed">
#!/bin/sh --login
</pre>
<p>By adding <e>--login</e> to the end of the <e>#! /bin/sh</e> line
we ensure that KDE will read <path>/etc/profile</path> when starting
up a terminal.</p>

<p>Because Achim, Gentoo Linux's lead package guru, is a genius, the
KDE ebuild configures KDE quite well all by itself.  The KDM display
manager should work just by starting it.</p>
<pre># <i>kdm</i></pre>
<p>You should be able to log in and see KDE in full working order.
Of course sound shouldn't be working yet, so you miss the annoying
KDE start-up sound, but we'll fix that in a moment.  Open a 
konsole, type <c>ls /usr/bin</c> (or anything else that more than fills 
the konsole window), and see if the mouse wheel lets
you scroll up and down in the konsole window.  It really should
work!</p>

<p>All that's left is to make sure that X comes up when Gentoo boots.
Edit <path>/etc/rc.d/config/basic</path> so that 
<e>DISPLAYMANAGER="kdm"</e>.  Now we just need to make sure that the
<e>xdm</e> start-up script is read when booting runlevel 4 (Gentoo's
default runlevel for X) and change <path>/etc/inittab</path> so that
runlevel 4 is the default runlevel.</p>
<pre>
# <i>rc-update add xdm</i>
# <i>vim /etc/inittab</i>
</pre>
<pre caption="the initdefault line, configured to start kdm (runlevel 4)">
id:4:initdefault:
</pre>
<p>Reboot, and see if X comes up!</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Sound</title>
<section>
<title>Standard Kernel Sound Modules</title>
<body>
<p>Out of the box, Gentoo Linux doesn't support the standard
kernel modules.  You'll have to recompile the kernel. Generally,
we prefer Alsa over the standard modules since they perform
better and have niftier features (see below for Alsa instructions.)
For standard kernel sound, install the <path>linux-sources</path>
ebuild:</p>
<pre>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/sys-kernel/linux-sources</i>
# <i>emerge linux-sources-x.y.z.ebuild</i>
</pre>
<p>The linux-sources ebuild installs the sources into /usr/src,
and you can then compile the kernel (and your sound module)
in the usual manner 
(<uri>http://www.linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO.html</uri>).
If you choose to compile the sound driver as a module (not
compile it directly into the kernel), they you need to add
the module name (without the .o extension) to 
<path>/etc/rc.d/config/modules</path>.</p>
<p>
Reboot the machine.  With any luck the appropriate sound driver 
should now be loaded.  To actually produce sound, a few more steps
are required.
</p>
<pre>
# <i>cd /dev</i>
# <i>/usr/sbin/MAKEDEV audio</i>
#
# <i>cat /opt/kde2.1/share/sounds/pop.wav &gt; /dev/dsp</i>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/media-sound/sox</i>
# <i>emerge sox-x.y.z.ebuild</i>
# <i>play /opt/kde2.1/share/sounds/pop.wav</i>
</pre>
<p>
If any sound at all results from cat'ing the .wav file to 
<path>/dev/dsp</path>, then sound is probably working.
By emerge'ing sox one can use the <c>play</c> command to 
play .wav files (and, unlike using <c>cat</c>, the .wav file
should sound good when using <c>play</c>).
</p>
<!-- 
found that when running <e>devfs</e> the /dev/MAKEDEV script
would be missing.  Help? Well, you shouldn't need to run MAKEDEV if you're
using devfs (maybe to get /dev/dsp created?), but if you need it, its real home is in /usr/sbin (/dev/MAKEDEV is
a symlink.  I changed the text to reflect this. [drobbins]
-->
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Alsa</title>
<body>

<p>Gentoo Linux does support Alsa for sound using the default kernel.  Alsa can
be run with or without <e>devfs</e>.  One note; if you've installed a new
<path>sys-kernel/linux-sources</path> package, make sure that your Linux kernel
has sound support enabled, and that <c>alsa</c> is defined in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>'s <c>USE</c> variable (important!).  Then, merge the
<path>sys-kernel/linux-extras</path> package that matches the linux-sources
that you are currently using.  The <path>linux-extras</path> ebuild is a special
ebuild that uses the sources in <path>/usr/src/linux</path> to compile and install
all necessary extra modules (like Alsa) and kernel-specific tools, like the LVM
utilities.</p>

<pre>
# <i>vim /etc/make.conf</i>
<comment>above, make sure that "alsa" is in the USE variable</comment>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/sys-kernel/linux-extras</i>
# <i>emerge linux-extras-x.y.z.ebuild</i>
<comment>the Alsa modules will now be installed</comment>
# <i>depmod -a</i>
</pre>
<p>
I am going to assume
here that you have <e>devfs</e> enabled; if you don't then please
see the Gentoo FAQ:
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/doc/faq.html</uri>.
</p>
<pre>
# <i>vim /etc/rc.d/config/modules</i>
</pre>
<pre caption="modules.conf with Alsa modules">
# Put modules to be loaded, with arguments, one per line
# The following lines will be called with "modprobe"
  
snd-card-ens1371
snd-pcm-oss

</pre>
<p>
You'll want to replace <e>snd-card-ens1371</e> with the
appropriate sound card for your system.  Look in
<path>/lib/modules/[kernel version]/misc/</path>
for a list of modules.  If you'd like to have OSS compatibility, it's
a very good idea to make sure the <e>snd-pcm-oss</e> line is also in there.
</p>
<warn>
Whatever you do, don't add kernel modules to 
<path>/etc/modules.conf</path>.  The <path>/etc/modules.conf</path>
file is autogenerated at boot time, so any changes made there will 
be lost.
</warn>
<p>Now we set up the <e>kerneld</e> aliases.</p>
<pre>
# <i>vim /etc/modules/2.4.4-ac5</i>
</pre>
<figure link="/images/kmod.png" short="kmod fig"/>
<p>
Again, you'll want to replace <e>snd-card-ens1371</e> with
your sound card.  
</p>
<p>We still have to help out <e>devfs</e>, however.
Add the following to <path>/etc/devfsd.conf</path>.</p>
<pre>
# <i>vim /etc/devfsd.conf</i>
</pre>
<figure link="/images/devfsd.png" short="devfsd image"/>
<p>
Reboot, and all of the sound stuff should be loaded.  You won't
hear any sound yet, though, because alsa keeps all sound channels
muted by default.
</p>
<pre>
# <i>amixer</i>

Group 'Input Gain',0
  Capabilities: volume mute jointly-mute
  Channels: Front-Left Front-Right
  Limits: min = 0, max = 15
  Front-Left: 11 [73%] [mute] [---]
  Front-Right: 11 [73%] [mute] [---]
Group 'Master Mono',0
  Capabilities: volume mute capture exclusive-capture
  Capture exclusive group: 1
  Channels: Front-Left Front-Right
  Limits: min = 0, max = 31
  Front-Left: 23 [74%] [mute] [---]
  Front-Right: 23 [74%] [mute] [---]
Group 'Headphone',0
  Capabilities: volume mute jointly-mute
  Channels: Front-Left Front-Right
  Limits: min = 0, max = 31
  Front-Left: 0 [0%] [mute] [---]
  Front-Right: 0 [0%] [mute] [---]
Group 'Master',0
  Capabilities: volume mute jointly-mute capture exclusive-capture
  Capture exclusive group: 1
  Channels: Front-Left Front-Right
  Limits: min = 0, max = 63
  Front-Left: 50 [79%] [mute] [---]
  Front-Right: 50 [79%] [mute] [---]
<comment>[chopped for brevity]</comment>

# <i>amixer set Master 100 unmute</i>
# <i>amixer set PCM 100 unmute</i>
# <i>aplay /opt/kde2.1/share/sounds/pop.wav</i>
</pre>
<p>
After installing the alsa utilities we use <c>amixer</c> to 
unmute the Master and PCM sound channels and to set their volume
to 100%.  We check to see if sound is working by using the 
<c>aplay</c> (alsa play) command.  If you hear a pop, then sound
is indeed working.  Then, adjust the volume settings to your liking;
the ncurses-based <c>alsamixer</c> is a great way to get them "just so".
When you reboot your system, the <path>/etc/rc.d/init.d/alsa</path>
script will properly save and restore your volume settings.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sound and KDE</title>
<body>
<p>
KDE has some nice sound utilities, including the KDE sound mixer 
<c>kmix</c>.  
</p>
<pre>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/kde-apps/kdemultimedia</i>
# <i>emerge kdemultimedia-x.y.z.ebuild</i>
# <i>kmix</i>
</pre>
<note>If kmix cannot find a mixer, then it probably thinks you don't
have sound support.  Log out and remove ~/.kde and ~/Desktop (the latter
may not be necessary), then log in again.  This time it should find 
the sound mixer properly.
</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Mail</title>
<section>
<title>Postfix -- Install and Configure</title>
<body>
<p>
Coming soon!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Postfix Testing (with Mutt)</title>
<body>
<p>
Coming soon!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Printing</title>
<section>
<title>Simple printing -- PDQ</title>
<body>
<p>
Coming soon!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Full-fledged printing -- CUPS</title>
<body>
<p>
Coming soon!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Samba</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Coming soon!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
