<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide>
<title>dynfw Dynamic Firewall Tools, v1.0</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<abstract>
Firewalls all good and fun, but what do you do when you need to make rapid,
complex changes to your iptables-based firewall rules?  Easy -- use the dynfw
Dynamic Firewall Tools, a collection of robust bash scripts that are designed
to work with nearly any existing iptables-based firewall configuration.  You
can use these scripts to increase your network security and responsiveness, and
as inspiration for your own creative designs.
</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>19 Apr 2001</date>

<chapter>
<title>dynfw</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>The dynfw scripts originated from an article I wrote for <uri link="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks">IBM developerWorks</uri> that showed how to make a firewall more responsive by creating scripts that automate common "firewall-tweaking" tasks,
such as blocking an IP, ratelimiting a host, etc.  The reason for the scripts is simple -- when you're in a crisis, you don't
want to make changes to your master firewall script in a frantic state.  Instead, you want to have an already-existing and
easy-to-use mechanism to make those changes for you, eliminating the possibility of error and allowing immediate response.
The following scripts are included in <path link="dynfw-1.0.tar.gz">dynfw-1.0.tar.gz</path>:

<p>You can read the original <uri link="http://www.ibm.com/developerWorks">IBM developerWorks</uri> article <uri>here</uri>,
which explains how to use the scripts.</p>
<p>You can download the current version of dynfw here: <path link="dynfw-1.0.tar.gz">dynfw-1.0.tar.gz</path>.</p>
<p>The dynfw Dynamic Firewall Tools are Copyright 2001 Gentoo Technologies, Inc. and distributed under the GNU Public License.You are encouraged to send any bug fixes or improvements to these tools to <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>.</p>


<table>
<tr><th>Script</th><th>Description</th></tr>
<tr><ti><path>ipdrop</path></ti><ti>discard packets coming from a specific IP</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>ipblock</path></ti><ti>discard as above, but send an TCP reset if applicable</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>tcplimit</path></ti><ti>limits new connections to a local port to a certain rate (per sec,minute,hour or day)</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>user-outblock</path></ti><ti>prevents a specific UID (user) from establishing outbound connections</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>

