<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide type="project" link="/projects/dynfw.html">
<title>dynfw Dynamic Firewall Tools, v1.0</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<version>1.0.1</version>
<date>30 Jul 2001</date>

<chapter>
<title>dynfw</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>Firewalls all good and fun, but what do you do when you need to make rapid,
complex changes to your netfilter-based firewall?  Instead of feverishly
hacking away at a complex master firewall script, use the dynfw Dynamic
Firewall Tools.  This collection of robust bash scripts have been designed to
work with nearly any existing netfilter-based firewall configuration.  By using
these scripts, you'll be able to make near-immediate changes to your firewall
configuration without risk of misconfiguration, resulting in vastly improved
network security and responsiveness.  The dynfw firewall scripts were
originally featured in <uri
link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-fw/?n-l-4191">this
IBM developerWorks article</uri>.</p>

<p>You can download the current version of dynfw here:
<uri>dynfw-1.0.1.tar.gz</uri>.</p> 

<note>The dynfw Dynamic Firewall Tools are
Copyright 2001 Gentoo Technologies, Inc. and distributed under the GNU General Public
License.  You are encouraged to send any bug fixes or improvements to these
tools to <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail> so that they
can be rolled into the official release.</note>


<p>The following scripts are included in <path>dynfw-1.0.1.tar.gz</path>:
</p>
<p>
<table>
<tr><th>Script</th><th>Description</th></tr>
<tr><ti><path>install.sh</path></ti><ti>the install script -- run this first</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dynfw.sh</path></ti><ti>the dynfw global support script -- used by all dynfw tools</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>ipdrop</path></ti><ti>discard packets coming from a specific IP</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>ipblock</path></ti><ti>discard as above, but send an TCP reset if applicable</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>tcplimit</path></ti><ti>ratelimit new connections to a local TCP port</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>host-tcplimit</path></ti><ti>ratelimit new connections from a specific host</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>user-outblock</path></ti><ti>prevents a specific UID (user) from establishing outbound connections</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changelog</title>
<body>

<p><e>1.0.1</e>: sh-compatibility fixes; <c>==</c> changed to <c>=</c> (oops!)</p>
<p><e>1.0</e>: Initial release.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>

