<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!-- $Id: gentoo-howto.xml,v 1.14 2001/05/23 01:27:41 drobbins Exp $ -->

<guide link="/doc/gentoo-howto.html">
<title>Gentoo Linux Developers HOWTO</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="pete@gentoo.org">Peter Gavin</mail></author>
<abstract>This document describes the Gentoo Linux Portage system, how
to create new packages for Gentoo, and is also meant to be somewhat of
a standard for the Gentoo Developers. It is a work in progress, and is
constantly being updated and changed. It is by no means
complete.</abstract>
<version>0.55</version>
<date>20 May 2001</date>

<!--

Contents

I. Introduction
II. The Portage Tree
  A. What (Not) to Put in the Portage Tree
  B. Categories
  C. The files Directory
III. .ebuild Files
  A. Naming .ebuild Files
  B. Contents of an .ebuild File
  C. Rules for Writing an .ebuild File
IV. Filesystem Locations
  A. Introduction to the FHS
  B. How to Fit Your Packages into the Filesystem
V. The Portage Scripts and Utilities
  A. Public Scripts
  B. Private Scripts
VI. Package Dependencies
    
-->


<chapter>
<title>The Portage tree</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body><p>The portage tree is a heirarchy, in which the first level is the category,
and the second is the name of the package.
</p></body>
</section>

<section>
<title> What (not) to put in the Portage tree</title>
<body><p>The Portage tree should only include ebuild files, and other
files in the <path>files</path> directory for each package. Generally, no binary
files should be placed in the portage tree. No files that can
be downloaded from other sources (such as patches written by
other people) should be put here. No patches you write
yourself should be compressed.
</p></body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Categories</title>
<body><p>The categories are defined as follows:</p>
<table><tr><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-admin</path></ti><ti>non-critical system administration utilities</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-arch</path></ti><ti>non-critical archival/compression utilities </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-cdr</path></ti><ti> CD recording utilities </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-doc</path></ti><ti>application documentation </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-editors</path></ti><ti>non-critical text editors </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-emulation</path></ti><ti>packages for emulating other systems/OSes </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-misc</path></ti><ti>applications that don't fit anywhere else </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-office</path></ti><ti>office-type (word processing, spreadsheet, etc.) packages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-shells</path></ti><ti>non-critical shells and command interpreters </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>app-text</path></ti><ti>text processing, spell checkers, and document formatting packages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-db</path></ti><ti>database libraries </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-java</path></ti><ti>java classes/packages/etc.  </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-lang</path></ti><ti>compilers and interpreters for different languages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-libs</path></ti><ti>miscellaneous developer's libraries </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-perl</path></ti><ti>perl modules </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-python</path></ti><ti>python modules </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-ruby</path></ti><ti>ruby modules </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>dev-util</path></ti><ti>various developers utilities </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>gnome-apps</path></ti><ti>applications for GNOME </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>gnome-base</path></ti><ti>base GNOME packages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>gnome-libs</path></ti><ti>non-essential GNOME libraries </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>gnome-office</path></ti><ti>office packages for gnome </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>kde-apps</path></ti><ti>applications for KDE </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>kde-base</path></ti><ti>base KDE packages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>kde-i18n</path></ti><ti>KDE internationalization packages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>media-gfx</path></ti><ti>graphics-related programs </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>media-libs</path></ti><ti>  libraries for manipulating different media, including accessing multimedia peripherals of your computer (sound card, video card, etc.) </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>media-sound</path></ti><ti>programs related to sound, including cd-audio and sound encoding </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>media-video</path></ti><ti>programs related to video, including video codecs and players </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-analyzer</path></ti><ti>network usage statistics monitors/analyzers </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-dialup</path></ti><ti>network dialup clients and servers such as pppd </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-fs</path></ti><ti>network filesystems </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-ftp</path></ti><ti>ftp servers and clients </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-irc</path></ti><ti>irc servers and clients </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-libs</path></ti><ti>networking-related libraries </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-mail</path></ti><ti>MTAs and MUAs </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-misc</path></ti><ti>miscellaneous servers, clients, firewalls, etc. </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-nds</path></ti><ti>NIS/NIS+ and other network directory services </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-print</path></ti><ti>print servers and clients </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>net-www</path></ti><ti>http/www servers and clients </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>sys-apps</path></ti><ti>system-critical applications and utilities </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>sys-devel</path></ti><ti>base development packages, such as gcc and make </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>sys-kernel</path></ti><ti>Linux kernels and kernel source packages </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>sys-libs</path></ti><ti>system-critical libraries such as glibc </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>x11-base</path></ti><ti>base X packages, such as XFree86 and drivers for various video cards </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>x11-libs</path></ti><ti>widget sets and other X-specific libraries</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>x11-terms</path></ti><ti>X-based terminal emulators </ti></tr>
<tr><ti><path>x11-wm</path></ti><ti>X window managers </ti></tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>The files Directory</title>
<body><p>Under each package subdirectory is a <path>files</path> directory. You
should place any patches, configuration files, and other
auxillary files your package might require in this
directory. Patches you create yourself just to get your
package to build should be called <path>${PF}-gentoo.diff</path>. You
should not compress these diffs, since they should not be big
enough to require compressing, and cvs does not play well
with binary files.
</p><p>Please add a suffix or prefix such as <path>${PVR}</path> to the tail of every file you put into
the <path>files</path> directory, so that the files used for each
individual version of your ebuild scripts are distinguishable
from one another, and so that the changes between different
revisions are visible.
</p><p>If you have many files that should go into the files
directory, you should create a subdirectory <path>files/${PVR}</path>, and put all these files
in there. If you use this method, you do not need to suffix
the names of the files in this directory with the ebuild version.
</p></body>
</section>
</chapter>
	
<chapter>
<title>ebuild files</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body><p>ebuild files are the basis for the entire portage
system. They contain all the information required to build a
package, and every installed package requires one of these
files. ebuild files are essentially just bash scripts that
contain a few functions and environment variable settings. The
<c>ebuild</c> command takes care of the rest of the details, such as
merging the package into the filesystem and recording the
package into the package database.
</p></body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Naming ebuild Files</title>
<body><p>ebuild file names are in four sections:</p>
<p>The first section is the package name, which should only
contain lowercase letters, the digits 0-9, and hyphen ('-')
characters.
</p><p>The second section is the version of the package, which should
normally be the same as the version on the main source
tarball. The version is normally made up of two or three numbers
separated by periods, such as <c>1.2</c> or <c>4.5.2</c> (although very long period-separated number sequences <e>are</e> supported), and may have a
single letter immediately following the last digit, e.g., <c>1.4b</c>
or <c>2.6h</c>. This letter should <e>not</e> be used to signify alpha or
beta status for the package. There are four special suffixes that
may be used for these packages: <c>_alpha</c>, <c>_beta</c>, <c>_pre</c> and <c>_rc</c>. Each
of these suffixes may be immediately followed my a number,
e.g., <c>linux-2.4.0_pre10</c>.  Assuming identical version parts, an <c>_alpha</c> package is
older than <c>_beta</c>, <c>_beta</c> older than <c>_pre</c>, and <c>_pre</c> older than <c>_rc</c>.
An <c>_rc</c> package is older than a package without an underscore prefix (i.e. <c>linux-2.4.0</c>),
and <c>linux-2.4.0</c> is older than a package with a single letter prefix, i.e. <c>linux-2.4.0b</c>.
As you would expect, the <c>linux-2.4.0b</c> package is considered older than <c>linux-2.4.0c</c>.
All this versioning information is important, as Portage uses it internally to determine whether one package
or ebuild is newer than another with the same category and name.
</p>

<p>The third section of the package name is the Gentoo Linux-specific <e>revision</e> number,
which is specified by <c>-r#</c>, where <c>#</c> is a number,
e.g. <c>package-4.5.3-r3</c>. This revision number is independent of
the version of the source tarball, but if you need to make
non-trivial changes to your ebuild file, you should copy the
ebuild file to a new file with the revision number
incremented by 1. Initial releases normally have no revision
number, e.g. <c>package-4.5.3</c> and default to a revision of zero.

</p><p>The fourth section of the ebuild file name is always the
<c>.ebuild</c> extension.
</p></body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Contents of an ebuild File</title>
<body><p>1. Variable Settings:</p>
<p>The first part of every ebuild file is made up of a number of
variable settings. The variables you can set are:</p>
<table>
<tr><ti><c>P</c></ti><ti>the name name and version of the package; you should not need to set this, as it is determined from the name of the ebuild file</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>A</c></ti><ti>the name (without the path) of the main archive file for your package</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>S</c></ti><ti>the source directory for your package; normally ${WORKDIR}/${P}</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>DESCRIPTION</c></ti><ti>a short, one line description of your package</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>SRC_URI</c></ti><ti>the URIs for every source file in your package, separated by whitespace; normally the first one is something like &quot;ftp://ftp.company.com/pub/somepackage/${A}&quot;</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>HOMEPAGE</c></ti><ti>your package's homepage</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>DEPEND</c></ti><ti>build dependencies; see the section <uri link="#dependencies">Package Dependencies</uri></ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>RDEPEND</c></ti><ti>runtime dependencies; see the section <uri link="#dependencies">Package Dependencies</uri></ti></tr>
</table>
<p>2. ebuild Functions</p>
<p>There are a number of different functions that you can define in ebuild files that control the building and installation process of your package.</p>
<table>
<tr><ti><c>src_unpack</c></ti><ti>Use this function to unpack your sources and apply patches, and run autoconf/automake/etc. if necessary. By default, unpacks the packages in <c>${A}</c> and applies <c>${PF}-gentoo.diff</c>. The default starting directory is <c>${BUILDDIR}</c>.</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>src_compile</c></ti><ti>Use this function to configure and build the package. Default starting directory is <c>${S}</c>.</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>src_install</c></ti><ti>Use this function install the package to an image in <c>${D}</c>. If your package uses automake, you can do this simply with <c>make DESTDIR=${D} install</c>. <emph>Make sure your package installs all its files using <c>${D}</c> as the root!</emph></ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>pkg_preinst</c></ti><ti>The commands in this function are run just prior to merging a package image into the filesystem.</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>pkg_postinst</c></ti><ti>The commands in this function are run just following merging a package image into the filesystem.</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>pkg_prerm</c></ti><ti>The commands in this function are run just prior to unmerging a package image from the filesystem.</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>pkg_postrm</c></ti><ti>The commands in this function are run just following unmerging a package image from the filesystem.</ti></tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Rules for writing an ebuild File</title>
<body><p>Since ebuild files are really just shell scripts, you should use your editor's
shell-script mode for editing them. You should use proper indentation, using only tab characters --
no spaces. Make sure you set up your editor to put tabstops at 4 spaces. Always make sure you use braces around your environment variables; e.g. <c>${P}</c> instead of just <c>$P</c>.</p>
<p>TODO: add stuff about emacs &amp; vi.</p></body>
</section>

<section>
<title><c>USE</c> Variables</title>

<body><p>The USE variable is set in <path>/etc/make.conf</path>. It
contains several keywords, normally called &quot;USE variables&quot;
by the developers, separated by spaces, that when present, enable and
disable certain features of packages that you install. You can check
for the presence of a USE variable in an <c>ebuild</c> that you create
using the <c>use &lt;variable&gt;</c> command. The <c>use</c> command
prints out the name of every variable that is present in both
<c>USE</c> and its command line. You would normally use this like
so:</p>
<p><c>if [ &quot;`use X`&quot; ]; then commands; fi</c></p>
<p>USE variables can also be used to set dependencies. For example,
you may only want to require a package if a certain USE variable is set. This is done by using the syntax <c>variable? (package-1.0-r1)</c> in the DEPEND variable for your ebuild. In this example, <c>package-1.0-r1</c> will only be required if <c>variable</c> is present in your <c>USE</c> setting.</p>
<p>The following USE variables are currently used in Gentoo Linux:</p>
<table>
<tr><th>Variable</th><th>Description</th><th>Used By</th></tr>
<tr><ti>X</ti><ti>enable X11 features</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>alsa</ti><ti>enable the Advanced Linux Sound Architecture</ti><ti><c>sys-kernel</c> packages and others</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>berkdb</ti><ti>use the Berkeley DB libraries</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>bonobo</ti><ti>enable Bonobo</ti><ti><c>gnome</c> packages and others</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>esd</ti><ti>enable ESound</ti><ti><c>gnome</c> packages and others</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>gdbm</ti><ti>use GNU dbm</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>glibc22</ti><ti>use GNU libc 2.2</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>gnome</ti><ti>use GNOME; also enables use of GNOME related packages such as gdk-pixbuf</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>gpm</ti><ti>use gpm</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>kde</ti><ti>enable features of the K Desktop Environment</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>ldap</ti><ti>use ldap</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>lm_sensors</ti><ti>enable lm_sensors</ti><ti><c>sys-kernel</c> packages</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>lvm</ti><ti>enable the Linux Volume Manager</ti><ti><c>sys-kernel</c> packages</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>motif</ti><ti>enable Motif</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>mysql</ti><ti>enable MySQL</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>odbc</ti><ti>enable odbc</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>ogg</ti><ti>enable the Ogg multimedia libraries</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>opengl</ti><ti>use OpenGL 3D graphics</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>pcmcia-cs</ti><ti>enable PCMCIA</ti><ti><c>sys-kernel</c> packages</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>postgres</ti><ti>use PostgreSQL</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>qt</ti><ti>use the Qt widget set</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>readline</ti><ti>use readline</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>slang</ti><ti>use slang</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>ssl</ti><ti>use SSL</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>tcltk</ti><ti>use Tcl/TK</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>tcpd</ti><ti>use tcpd/tcp_wrappers</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>xfs</ti><ti>enable the SGI XFS journaling filesystem</ti><ti><c>sys-kernel</c> packages</ti></tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Filesystem Locations</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction to the FHS</title>
<body>
<p>The filesystem standard used in Gentoo Linux is the FHS,
short for Filesystem Heirarchy Standard, version 2.0. A simplified
description of the standard is given here; for a complete
specification go to <uri>http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/docs/fhs/</uri>.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>How to fit your packages into the filesystem</title>
<body><p>Usually, if the package uses autoconf and automake, the
default installation destinations are fine, with a few exceptions:</p>
<ul>
<li>most packages go into prefix <path>/usr</path>; X11 specific programs and libraries can go into prefix <path>/usr/X11R6</path>; GNOME packages go into <path>/opt/gnome</path>; and KDE packages go into <path>/opt/kde</path></li>
<li>man pages always go into <path>${prefix}/share/man</path>, not <path>${prefix}/man</path>; you can set this with <c>./configure --mandir=${prefix}/share/man</c></li>
<li>info pages always go into <path>${prefix}/share/info</path>, not <path>${prefix}/info</path>; you can set this with <c>./configure --mandir=${prefix}/share/info</c></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Portage scripts and utilities</title>

<section>
<title>Public scripts</title>
<body><p>These are scripts used by the system-administrator to install and remove packages, and maintain the package database.</p>
<p><c>ebuild</c></p>
<p><c>ebuild</c> is the main engine of the Portage system; it performs all major tasks such as unpacking, compiling, installing, merging, and unmerging packages. It is called using the command: <c>ebuild path/to/package.ebuild command</c>. The commands available are:</p>
<table>
<tr><th>Command</th><th>Description</th><th>Related <c>ebuild</c> Function</th></tr>
<tr><ti><c>depend</c></ti><ti>displays the dependencies required to build the package</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>check</c></ti><ti>checks that the package dependencies are fulfilled</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>rcheck</c></ti><ti>checks that the package runtime dependencies are fulfilled</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>merge</c></ti><ti>unpacks, compiles, installs, and merges the package into your filesystem</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>qmerge</c></ti><ti>merges the package into your filesystem, assuming that the the unpack, compile, and install stages have already been executed</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>unpack</c></ti><ti>unpacks the source tarballs into the work directory</ti><ti><c>src_unpack</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>compile</c></ti><ti>compiles the package</ti><ti><c>src_compile</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>rpm</c></ti><ti>creates an RPM from the package</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>package</c></ti><ti>creates a Gentoo <c>tbz2</c> package</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>prerm</c></ti><ti>executes the pre-removal stage of the package</ti><ti><c>pkg_prerm</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>postrm</c></ti><ti>executes the post-removal stage of the package</ti><ti><c>pkg_postrm</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>preinst</c></ti><ti>executes the pre-installation stage of the package</ti><ti><c>pkg_preinst</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>postinst</c></ti><ti>executes the post-installation stage of the package</ti><ti><c>pkg_postinst</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>config</c></ti><ti>sets up a default configuration once the package is merged</ti><ti><c>src_config</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>touch</c></ti><ti>updates the mtimes for each source archive in the package</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>clean</c></ti><ti>cleans the work directory for the package</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>fetch</c></ti><ti>fetches the package source tarballs</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>digest</c></ti><ti>creates a digest file for the package</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>*<c>install</c></ti><ti>installs the package into the image directory</ti><ti><c>src_install</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti><c>unmerge</c></ti><ti>unmerges the package from your filesystem</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
</table>
<p>Note: commands with an asterisk (*) are normally only used by the developer.</p>

<p><c>emerge</c></p>
<p><c>emerge</c> recursively merges a package and all of its dependencies into your filesystem.</p>

<p><c>pkgmerge</c></p>
<p><c>pkgmerge</c> merges a Gentoo <c>tbz2</c> package.</p>

<p><c>env-update</c></p>
<p><c>env-update</c> updates the configuration files (including, but not limited to <path>/etc/ld.so.conf</path> and <path>/etc/profile.env</path>) to include changes made by installed packages.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Private Scripts and Commands</title>
<body><p>These are scripts you can use in your ebuild files to perform common tasks.</p>
<table>
<tr><ti>dobin</ti><ti>installs the specified binaries into <path>DESTTREE/bin</path></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dodir</ti><ti>sets the target prefix (<path>DESTTREE</path>) for <c>dobin</c>, <c>dolib</c>, <c>doman</c>, etc.</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dodoc</ti><ti>installs the specified files into the packages documentation directory (<path>/usr/share/doc/${PF}</path>)</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>doexe</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dohard</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>doinfo</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>doins</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dolib</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dolib.a</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dolib.so</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>doman</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>domo</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>donewins</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dopython</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dosbin</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dosed</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>dosym</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>find-packages</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>find-requires</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>fowners</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>fperms</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>import-configsettings</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>import-settings</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>megadigest</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>megadownload</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>megatouch</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newbin</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newdoc</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newexe</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newins</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newlib.a</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newlib.so</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newman</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>newsbin</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>pkgmerge</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>pkgname</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>pmake</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>prepall</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>prepalldocs</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>prepallinfo</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>prepallman</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>try</ti><ti></ti></tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Package Dependencies</title>

<section>
<title>Why dependencies are important</title>
<body><p>(TODO)<!-- todo -->
</p></body>
</section>

<section>
<title>How to Specify Dependencies in Your ebuild Files</title>
<body><p>(TODO)<!-- todo -->
</p></body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
