<?xml version='1.0'?>
<mainpage id="about">
<title>About Gentoo Linux</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<version>1.0.3</version>
<date>09 Aug 2001</date>

<chapter>
<section>
<body>
		<fig link="/images/fishhead.gif"/><br/>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux in a paragraph</title>
<body>
		<p>
		<b>Gentoo Linux is a versatile and fast, completely free x86-based Linux
		distribution geared towards developers and network professionals.</b> 
		Unlike other distros,
		Gentoo Linux has an advanced package management system called <b>Portage</b>.
		<b>Portage</b> is a true ports system in the tradition of BSD ports, but is
		Python-based and sports a number of advanced features including
		dependencies, fine-grained package management, "fake" (OpenBSD-style)
		installs, safe unmerging, system profiles, virtual packages, config
		file management, and more.
		</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6 Features</title>
<body>
	<p>
	<b>Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6</b> (release candidate 6) features <b>Linux 2.4.10</b>+ and 
	a modern <b>GNU</b> development environment (<b>glibc-2.2.4</b>, <b>gcc 2.95.3</b>),
	<b>ReiserFS</b>, <b>ext3</b>, <b>LVM</b>, <b>ALSA</b>, 
	<b>PCMCIA-CS</b> and <b>lm_sensors</b> 
	support built-in to the kernel, <b>"vanilla"</b> (stock) kernel 
	packages/compatibility for those who prefer unpatched kernels,
	<b>Xfree86 4.1.0</b>, <b>OpenGL</b>, <b>KDE 2.2.2</b> and <b>GNOME 1.4</b>,
	tcp-wrappers, xinetd, <b>iptables</b> and Linux <b>QoS</b> tools,
	modern <b>qmail</b> (with optional <b>mysql</b> and <b>LDAP</b> support), 
	<b>postfix</b> and <b>exim</b> MTAs,
	<b>GRUB</b> boot loader (<b>LILO</b> is still available if you need it),
	<b>800+ up-to-date ebuild scripts</b> for your favorite apps, 
	a new <b>dependency- (or need-) based set of init scripts</b>, tons more, and
	of course <b>Portage</b> and a completely open design.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>More about Portage</title>
<body>
		<p><b>Portage allows you to set up Gentoo Linux the way <e>you</e> like
		it</b> -- with the optimization settings that you want, and with optional
		build-time functionality (like <b>GNOME</b>, <b>KDE</b>, <b>mysql</b>, 
		<b>ALSA</b>, <b>LDAP</b> support,
		etc.) enabled or disabled as you desire.  If you don't want <b>GNOME</b> on
		your system, your apps won't have optional <b>GNOME</b> support enabled, and
		if you do, then they will.  That's why we prefer thinking of Gentoo
		Linux as a <e>meta</e>-distribution or Linux <e>technology engine</e>.
		You decide what kind of system you want, and <b>Portage</b> will create it for
		you.</p>
		
		<p>We maintain an official Gentoo Linux <b>Portage tree</b> that contains
		the most recent versions of our ebuild autobuild scripts.  By updating
		your Portage tree, you gain instant access to the latest and greatest
		Linux technologies and applications.  Tell Portage what ebuild you'd
		like to install, and Portage will auto-download, unpack, patch,
		configure, compile and install the package.  Thanks to Portage
		auto-dependency resolution, you can install <b>KDE 2.2.2</b> or <b>GNOME 1.4</b>
		by typing in a single command, and the resultant installed binaries
		will be optimized and customized to your exact specifications.</p>

		<p><b>If this kind of power and flexibility appeals to you, then we
		encourage you to try Gentoo Linux for yourself.</b>  You won't be
		disappointed.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
