<?xml version='1.0'?>
<mainpage id="news">
<title>Gentoo Linux News</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<version>1.0.3</version>
<date>21 Sep 2001</date>

<newsitems>
	<news align="left" graphic="/images/icon-clock.png">
		<poster>drobbins</poster>
		<date>29 Aug 2001</date>
		<title>Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6 status update redux</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6 is almost here.</b>  Right now -- this very moment -- I'm compiling our <e>sixth</e> 1.0_rc6 build image (chrootable environment); our build images are the heart of Gentoo Linux.  Tons of bugs have been fixed since last week, and our build images are now quite solid.  And even though the build images are only for Gentoo Linux build testers (at least right now), some of our more saavy users have already used them to build functional pre-1.0_rc6 systems.  However, I don't recommend you do this unless you have a lot of time on your hands, since nearly all packages with initscripts need to be updated to work with our new dependency-based init system.  While this isn't difficult work, it's probably best if you let us get to it first. :) 
		</p>
		<p>
		<b>Also note that <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/library/l-fs2.html">Part 2 of my Advanced Filesystem Implementor's Guide</uri> is now up on <uri link="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux">IBM developerWorks</uri>.</b>  
In it, I show you how to configure and use ReiserFS in a production environment.  I also show you how to <e>tweak ReiserFS for maximum performance</e>, and also cover potential application/ReiserFS interactions that you should know about.  You can also read the <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-fs.html">first Filesystem Guide article here</uri>; it contains a very good introduction to journalling filesystem technology and explains the design philosophy behind ReiserFS.
		</p>
		</body>
	</news>
	
	<news align="right" graphic="/images/icon-linux.png">
		<poster>drobbins</poster>
		<date>21 Aug 2001</date>
		<title>Keychain, Hackfest/Development update</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>I've now added a <uri link="/projects/keychain">Keychain</uri> project page to the site</b>.  For those who don't
		know, <c>keychain</c> is a special <uri link="http://www.openssh.com">OpenSSH</uri>-compatible key management app
		that interfaces with <c>ssh-agent</c> and makes it possible to set up secure connections easily and conveniently
		-- without typing in a passphrase every time.  The second part of my RSA/DSA authentication article will appear soon
		on <uri link="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux">IBM developerWorks</uri>.  In the mean time, you may want to check out <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/library/l-keyc.html">my first RSA/DSA article</uri>, which covers
		OpenSSH RSA/DSA key-based authentication basics.</p>
		<p><b>Also, the Hackfest was a big success!</b>  Tons of bugs were stomped, and we now have the second revision of
		our experimental Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6 build image (with <e>glibc 2.2.4</e>) so that developers can continue their testing.  Revision three should
		be out in the next few days and should contain <e>kernel 2.4.8-rc6+</e>.  Along the way, we continue to wipe out huge numbers of bugs, and Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6 certainly looks like it's going to be the most refined version of Gentoo Linux yet.
		</p>
		</body>
	</news>
	<news align="left" graphic="/images/icon-linux.png">
		<poster>drobbins</poster>
		<date>16 Aug 2001</date>
		<title>New IBM dW tutorial, Hackfest, LWN</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>My new <uri link="http://www-105.ibm.com/developerworks/education.nsf/linux-onlinecourse-bytitle/0FB4D16BD2C3E83E86256AA2005244D1?OpenDocument">Linux Backup Tutorial</uri> is now online</b> in the <uri link="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/">IBM developerWorks Linux Zone</uri>.  In it, I show you how to create a set of automated tape backup scripts based upon <c>star</c>, a high-performance <c>tar</c> archiver that is especially well suited to tape backups.  I also unravel the mysteries behind the <c>mt</c> command and <e>tape block sizes</e>; so if you're curious, give it a read.  Registration is required, but worth it :)
		</p>
		<p><b>Lamer (also known as Ben Lutgens of <uri link="http://www.sistina.com">Sistina Software, Inc.</uri>) asked me to announce the semi-official Gentoo Linux Hackfest</b>, this weekend (Aug 17-19) in the <c>#gentoo</c> IRC channel on the <uri link="http://www.openprojects.net">Open Projects IRC Network</uri>.  The goal of this Hackfest is to allow Gentoo Linux users to report bugs and have Gentoo Linux developers fix them on CVS/rsync in real time!  Great idea, lamer!</p>
		<p>And third, <b>a new issue of <uri link="http://www.lwn.net">the Linux Weekly News</uri> is now online</b>.  I'm a big fan of LWN, and if you want to keep up with what is going on in the Linux world, it's always a good idea to head over to <uri>http://www.lwn.net</uri> every Thursday and give it a read.</p>
		</body>
	</news>
<news align="right" graphic="/images/icon-stick1.png">
		<poster>drobbins</poster>
		<date>14 Aug 2001</date>
		<title>Web site updates</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		<b>Welcome to the new gentoo.org!</b>  Yes, we <e>finally</e> have news on the site; I hope
		you like the new look and functionality.  Now that we have a news page, we can keep everyone
		up-to-date with the latest Gentoo Linux developments much more easily.
		</p>
		<p>
		
Right now, the XML component of the news system is complete, and Thread (dev-wiki coder) is working
		on a news database backend.  When finished, you'll be able to post comments relating to the
		news items.  Should be pretty neat.  
		</p><p>
		<e>I'm sure that you've also noticed the recent addition
		of advertising to the site</e>.  The purpose of these ads is (as you might guess) to help offset
		costs involved with Gentoo Linux development.  <e>I should also mention that <b>I actually use</b> and have very high opinions of all the
		products that you see advertised here.</e>  Both <c>cvs.gentoo.org</c>
		and <c>inventor.gentoo.org</c> use Crucial RAM; I (and the Gentoo Linux development team) rely on it daily. 
		</p><p>
		And while you may be surprised to see an ad for an online auto loan company on gentoo.org, I absolutely <e>love</e>
		PeopleFirst.com.  Thanks to PeopleFirst, I was able to get a car loan with an APR <e>2%
		lower</e> than what I could get from local credit unions, saving me hundreds of dollars.  And they have
		always been great to deal with, from the moment I first contacted them.  If you have any questions
		about our advertisers, please feel free to <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">email me</mail> or chat with
		me on <c>#gentoo</c>.  <e>I want <b>you</b> (and myself!) to feel comfortable with the advertising
		on the site, so I will only advertise top-quality products.</e> 
		</p>
		<p>
		Special thanks to Thread for his work on the dev-wiki and his current work on the News database
		backend, and much thanks to Jano for providing us with the cool stickman graphic that you see on
		the left. :)
		</p>
		</body>
	</news>
</newsitems>
</mainpage>
