<?xml version='1.0'?>
<mainpage id="download">
<title>Gentoo Linux -- download and installation!</title>
<author title="Chief Architect"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<version>2.2</version>
<date>19 Sep 2001</date>

<chapter>
<title>All about Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6</title>
<section>
<title>Status</title>
<body>

<p> <b>We now have a very stable prerelease version of the Gentoo Linux build
image available for download, in both .tbz2 and bootable ISO forms</b>.  Quite
a few people have used this technique to create their own Gentoo Linux 1.0_rc6
systems.  While our Portage tree hasn't been 100% updated to work with 1.0_rc6
(we're working on getting all the initscripts converted over to our new
format), most packages <e>will</e> work perfectly.  If you've been anxiously
waiting to run 1.0_rc6, here's your opportunity!  </p>

<p><b>You can find the 1.0_rc6 build images and ISOs at
<uri>http://www.ibiblio.org/gentoo/snapshots/build/ix86-linux-gnu</uri>.</b>
ISO images should work with any modern bootable CD-ROM, IDE or SCSI.
You can find
the most recent installation instructions for the ISO install <uri link="/doc/build.html">here,
in the 1.0_rc6 "from source" Installation Guide</uri>.  Right now, we don't
have instructions for the .tbz2 install, but the installation process is very
similar to that of the ISO, and you should be able to use the ISO docs.  All
you'll need to do is chroot from an existing Linux 2.4-based distribution
rather than the boot CD.  Just perform all the "before chroot" steps from your
existing Linux distro, such as using <c>fdisk</c> and creating and mounting
filesystems.  In fact, if your network is already configured under your
existing Linux distro, it should continue to work after the chroot, so you can
skip most of the network configuration steps needed in order to get emerge
rsync to work.  All you'll need to do is to update
<path>/mnt/gentoo/etc/resolv.conf</path> (the chrooted
<path>/etc/resolv.conf</path>) so that DNS name resolution works properly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
