<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide link="/doc/nvidia_tsg.html">
<title>nVidia Linux Driver Troubleshooting Guide</title>
<author><mail link="phoenix@minion.de">Christian Zander</mail></author>
<author><mail link="mthome@bbn.com">Michael Thome</mail></author>

<abstract>This document is a guide to getting the nVidia drivers working with X in Linux; please note that it is not specific to Gentoo Linux.</abstract>

<version>1.0.0</version>
<date>Feb 13 2001</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<section>
		<title>What now?</title>
		<body>
		<p>Allright, you've installed the nVidia Linux drivers and fired up X in anticipation of all the wonderful things it can do. For some reason however, things didn't quite
work out as expected and now you're sitting looking at a blank screen or, if you were lucky, at a nice console. while you can't deny the beauty of a 80x40 terminal you wouldn't mind fraggin' the guy next door ... what to do?</p>
		<p>Luckily, most problems you could have run into have already been encountered by
other people. even better, there are fixes to most of those problems. but: where to look for (and get) answers? this document may just be what you want.
		</p>
		<p>Before going any further - most of the information herein is what I have seen in
<c>#nvidia</c> (<uri link="http://www.openprojects.net">irc.openprojects.net</uri>) and my own experience with the drivers. I've also taken the liberty
to take some information from the driver and its documentation. The IRC channel mentioned is a good place to look for both help and various files/patches.</p>
		<p>You may want to check your system with the <c>nv_check.sh</c> script first. it can be
downloaded (like all the patches i refer to) from <c>iCE-DCC</c>, a DCC offer bot at home in the above IRC channel.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Feedback</title>
		<body>
		<p>For suggestions, questions, etc, email <mail link="phoenix@minion.de">Christian Zander</mail></p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>AGP/KERNEL</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<body>
		<p>As you may have noticed already, the nVidia driver needs a kernel level resource
manager to function properly. this resource manager is the NVdriver kernel module. among its responsibilities are access control to the device(s), locating and initializing certain aspects of the hardware, controlling the AGP driver, DMA to name some.</p>
		<p>It is extremely important that the kernel module works properly, or you will never have the fun that you were promised in exchange for $$.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>AGPGART vs. NVAGP</title>
		<body>
		<p>As far as linux is concerned, your nice AGP port is just another PCI slot and is
detected as such. since you want to use what AGP has to offer beyond that, you need a proper driver.
with the nVidia Linux drivers, you get to choose between nVidia's AGP driver that was ported from NT
(NVAGP) and AGPGART, which was/is developed by Jeff Hartmann and a number of contributors. AGPGART
is part of the official kernel (2.2.18+, 2.3.??+) and enabled in many distributions by default. Which one of the two you want to use largely depends on (1) your AGP chipset (2) your preferences.
		</p>
		<p>If everything worked out for you with whichever driver you chose to use, you need
not worry about this. chances are however, that things didn't quite work out for you (you're reading this).
		</p>
		<p>One way of figuring out if it is your AGP setup that is causing problems (and sometimes the only way to get things going at all) is to completely disable AGP support in the driver. to do this, you add this option to the <e>Screen</e> setion of your <path>XF86Config</path> file:
		</p>
		<pre>Option "<i>NvAgp</i>" "<i>0</i>"</pre>
		<p>Some combinations of drivers and AGP chipsets can make your system unstable or even unusable, so look out. these combinations should work (very incomplete, let me know about other configs):
		</p>
		<!--<p>Intel:</p>-->
		<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Chipset</th>
			<th>Driver</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>Intel</ti>
			<ti><pre>440BX   NVAGP   / AGPGART <comment># doesn't work for some people</comment>
810     NVAGP   / AGPGART
815(e)  NVAGP   / AGPGART <comment># w/ 815 patch</comment></pre></ti>
                 </tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>VIA</ti>
			<ti><!--<p>VIA:</p>--><pre>Apollo  AGPGART / NVAGP
MVP3    AGPGART
MVP4    AGPGART
KX133   NVAGP
KT133   NVAGP</pre></ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>Ali</ti>
			<ti><!--<p>Ali:</p>--><pre>...     AGPGART <comment># 2.4.0+,  2.2.18 w/ ALi patch</comment></pre>
		</ti></tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>SiS</ti>
			<ti><!--<p>SiS:</p>--><pre>...     AGPGART <comment># ?</comment></pre></ti>
		</tr>
		</table>
		<p>In case you're wondering what AGP chipset your mainboard may be using - either
consult your mainboard's documentation or try to retrieve the information from <path>/proc/pci</path>
		</p>
		<pre>$ <i>grep AGP /proc/pci</i></pre>
		<p>Now that you know what driver you want, how do you actually go about setting the system up to use it?</p>
        	<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Flag</th>
			<th>Effect</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>NVAGP</ti>
			<ti><!--
		<p>Compile the NVdriver kernel module with:</p>
		<pre>$ <i>make clean</i>
$ <i>make NVdriver BUILD_PARAMS=NOAGPGART</i>
# <i>make install</i></pre>--><p>Enable NVAGP support</p></ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>AGPGART</ti>
			<ti>Enable support for AGPGART in your kernel. no special action must be
taken thereafter, NVdriver will automagically be built with support for it. i strongly recomment
that you use at least 2.2.18 or a recent development kernel with AGPGART.</ti>
		</tr>
		</table>
		<p>When using NVAGP, compile the NVdriver kernel module with:</p>
		<pre>$ <i>make clean</i>
$ <i>make NVdriver BUILD_PARAMS=NOAGPGART</i>
# <i>make install</i></pre>
		<impo><p>Changes as of 0.9-6:</p>
		<p>Starting with this version, the driver will load the AGP driver dynamically when
X starts. Which driver it loads will be controlled by the NvAgp option in the Screen section of the
<path>XF86Config</path> file:</p></impo>
		<pre>Option "<i>NvAgp</i>" "<i>0</i>"  <comment># disable AGP support</comment>
Option "<i>NvAgp</i>" "<i>1</i>"  <comment># use NVAGP</comment>
Option "<i>NvAgp</i>" "<i>2</i>"  <comment># use AGPGART</comment></pre>
		<p>Make sure you don't have the 'other' AGP driver loaded when instructing X to load
e.g. NVAGP. some distributions load AGPGART by default - X will catch this case, but won't be able
to switch the AGP driver on the fly (see below).</p>
		<p>Bear in mind that switching AGP drivers or disabling them usually requires a
system reboot before the changes really take effect. loading different AGP drivers w/o a reboot may
cause lockups or general system instability.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>AGP Aperture</title>
		<body>
		<p>Physically, this is the amount of RAM that you allow your card to
use via the AGP interface (for textures, etc). while it is left
to you to decide on the value for this setting, it is generally
desirable to use no more than 1/2 of your RAM. 32M-64M seem to be
reasonable values. don't set this to a value equal to the amount
of RAM you have or even higher. AGPGART may lock your machine if
you do. (set this in your BIOS)
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>AGP Fast Writes</title>
		<body>
		<p>Meant to increase performance, this setting usually locks up
machines. in any case, the performance gains aren't worth the
hazzle. (set this in your BIOS)</p>
		<p>(alternatively, you can pass <c>NVreg_EnableAGPFW=0</c> to NVdriver)</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>AGP Speeds (1x, 2x, 4x)</title>
		<body>
		<p>This controls the bandwidth with which your AGP bus operates. while
most of todays chipsets support 4x operation, this can cause lockups
and strange behaviour with some of them. the driver knows about many
such flaws and enables workarounds. Via chipsets are forced to 2x
operation by default.
</p>
		<p>
you can influence the AGP speed setting with an option passed to
NVdriver:
</p>
           <pre># <i>modprobe NVdriver NVreg_ReqAGPRate=0x2</i> <codenote>0x1 | 0x2 | 0x4</codenote></pre>
		<p>
       or with an options entry in <path>modules.conf</path>:
		</p>
           <pre>alias char-major-195 NVdriver
           options NVdriver NVreg_ReqAGPRate=<i>0x2</i></pre>
		<p>
       (if you want 4x operation with Via chipsets, use <c>NVreg_EnableVia4x=1</c>)
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>AGP Workarounds &amp;&amp; AGPGART</title>
		<body>
		<p>
       as mentioned in the previous section, the driver enables a set of
       workarounds for certain AGP chipsets. starting with version 0.9-5 of
       the driver, these workarounds are applied to both NVAGP and AGPGART.
       if you don't want to use them with AGPGART (for whatever reason), you
       can disable the default behaviour with the <c>NVreg_UpdateKernelAGP=0</c>
       option to NVdriver.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
      IRQ / Assigning an Interrupt to VGA
		</title>
		<body>
		<p>
       the nVidia driver needs an interrupt assigned to your graphics
       adapter to work properly. make sure that you enable the '<c>assign
       IRQ to vga</c>' option in your BIOS (or however your BIOS calls it).
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
Building NVdriver
</title>
		<body><p>
building the NVdriver kernel module is straight forward in most
cases:
		</p>
<pre>$ make clean
$ <i>make NVdriver <codenote>optionally BUILD_PARAMS=NOAGPGART, see above</codenote></i>
# <i>make install</i></pre>
<p>
there are situations, however when this won't work out. i already
mentioned options that allow you to choose between AGPGART and NVAGP.
</p>
<p>
the driver assumes that you have your kernel headers installed in
<path>/usr/src/linux/include</path>. if that is not correct, use the <c>SYSINCLUDE</c>
option:
</p>
<pre>$ <i>make clean</i>
$ <i>make NVdriver SYSINCLUDE=/where/ever/your/headers/are</i>
# <i>make install</i></pre>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>
Character Special Files
		</title>
		<body><p>
nVidia's XFree86 driver module communicates with the NVdriver kernel
module through a set of character special files located in the <path>/dev</path>
directory. if they weren't created or have improper permissions, X
will fail.
		</p>
<pre>crw-rw----    1 root     video    195,   0 Jan  4 23:19 /dev/nvidia0
crw-rw----    1 root     video    195,   1 Jan  4 23:19 /dev/nvidia1
crw-rw----    1 root     video    195,   2 Jan  4 23:19 /dev/nvidia2
crw-rw----    1 root     video    195,   3 Jan  4 23:19 /dev/nvidia3
crw-rw----    1 root     video    195, 255 Jan  4 23:19 /dev/nvidiactl</pre>
		<p>
As you can see, I chose to make the files accessible only to root and
members of the group <c>video</c>. your choice may be different - in any
case, make sure that the user you're trying to run X as has access to
these files (read and write access).
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>devFS</title>
		<body><p>
       As of version 2.3.?? of the linux kernel, an alternative method has
       been introduced, the socalled <c>devFS</c>. while explaining the mechanism
       itself is out of the scope of this document, i want to note that a
       patch exists for NVdriver that makes it devFS aware.
		</p></body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>procFS</title>
		<body><p>
       starting with 0.9-6, the nVidia driver will provide information about
       your setup in <path>/proc/nv/card[0-3]</path>. There's a patch to enable part of
       that for 0.9-5.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>BIOS Repost</title>
		<body><p>
       the driver attempts to repost the card's bios when X starts to ensure
       that the card is in a state known to the driver. unfortunately, this
       causes problems with some cards. you can disable this behaviour with
       yet another option to NVdriver:
		</p>
		<pre>
           modprobe NVdriver NVreg_SkipBiosPost=<i>1</i>
		</pre>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>TNT SGRAM vs. SDRAM</title>
		<body><p>
       the driver detects the type of memory used on TNT cards by reading
       its embedded bios. unfortunately, some cards have been flashed with
       improper bioses. if you feel that this may be the case with your
       setup, you may want to try the <c>NVreg_VideoMemoryTypeOverride</c> option
       to NVdriver (<c>SDRAM = 1, SGRAM = 2</c>). this doesn't always work, see
       <path>os-registry.c</path> for details.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Kernel 2.4.0</title>
		<body><p>
       quite some changed since 2.2.x and lots of these changes affected the
       nVidia driver. you can get patches for this kernel series from <c>#nvidia</c>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>	
       "Ignoring changed section attributes for .modinfo"
		</title>
		<body><p>
         If this message annoys you, you'll want to comment out the
         offending line in <path>/usr/src/linux/include/linux/modules.h</path>. If you
         don't mind it - leave it alone, its harmless.
		</p></body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>XFree86 / OpenGL</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<body><p>
    before i start describing some of the most common problems with this
    part of the driver, i want to explain some things that are commonly
    misunderstood and seem to confuse a fair amount of people:
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>nVidia's Driver Architecture vs. DRI and DRM</title>
		<body><p>
       nVidia's driver does not make use of the Direct Rendering Interface
       that made its debut with XFree86 4.0.0. instead, nVidia chose to
       implement its own mechanism. the architectures are quite similar:
       both use a kernel level resource manager (NVdriver vs. DRM) and both
       provide a mechanism by means of which high performance OpenGL
       rendering can be achieved by allowing the OpenGL implementation to
       talk directly to the hardware instead of using GLX when running
       locally.
		</p></body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>nVidia's OpenGL Implementation vs. Mesa</title>
		<body><p>
       nVidia's driver comes with its own OpenGL implementation and does not
       use Mesa, which is shipped with XFree86. nVidia's OpenGL libraries
       are based on SGI's OpenGL 1.2 implementation and provide a set of
       extensions that allow making use of advanced features such as using
       S3TC compressed textures.
		</p></body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>nVidia's XFree86 Driver Module vs. XFree86's</title>
		<body><p>
       the <c>nv</c> driver module shipped with XFree86 has nothing in common
       with the 'nvidia' driver module provided by nVidia. it does not
       rely on a kernel module to operate, does not require an interrupt
       and 'only' supports 2D operation. starting with 4.0.2 it works on
       all of nVidia's graphics adapters, including GeForce 2 cards. if
       you installed a distribution with XFree86 4.0.x, you are likely to
       have this driver installed. it is a good idea to test your X
       installation by attempting to start X with the <c>nv</c> driver module.
		</p>
    		<p>I will now list some of the most common problems that people encounter
    with the nVidia drivers. many of the things listed here are covered in
    the official documentation included with the driver package, but since
    nobody seems to read it, i list them here anyway.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>libglx.a / libGLcore.a / libGL.so.1.2.303... (Mesa)</title>
		<body><p>
       my alltime favorites ... as mentioned above, nVidia's driver does
       not make use of the Mesa libraries shipped with XFree86 - in fact,
       it conflicts with them.
		</p>
       <warn>This is <e>the</e> most common error source</warn>
		<p>
       If your distribution installed and configured X for you, you are
       likely to have a Module section in your <path>XF86Config</path> that looks like
       this:
		</p>
<pre>Section "<i>Module</i>"
	...
	Load  "<i>glx</i>"
	Load  "<i>GLcore</i>"
	...
EndSection</pre>
	<p>
       These two statements are what you need to pay particular attention
       to:
	</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Load "glx"</title>
		<body><p>
          This instructs X to load the GLX extension module. with a default
          XFree86 installation, this translates to <path>libglx.a</path>. the nVidia
          driver provides its own GLX extension, <path>libglx.so</path>. this is where
          the fun begins: if you didn't remove <path>libglx.a</path>, X will continue to
          load <path>libglx.a</path>, which can't work with nVidia's driver.
		</p>
          <impo>Delete or rename <path>libglx.a</path> (<path>/usr/X11R6/lib/modules/extensions</path>)</impo>
	</body></section>

	<section>
		<title>Load "GLcore"</title>
		<body><p>
          Not much to say here other than that you don't want this line in
          your modules section. libGLcore.so as provided by nVidia will be
          loaded dynamically - don't load it as an X extension, it won't
          work.
		</p>
		<p>
          You can easily find out if you're loading <path>libglx.a</path> and/or
          libGLcore.a by looking at <path>/var/log/XFree86.0.log</path>:
		</p>
<pre>...
(II) LoadModule: "glx"
(II) Loading /usr/X11R6/lib/modules/extensions/libglx.a
(II) Module glx: vendor="The XFree86 Project"
	compiled for 4.0.1, module version = 1.0.0
	ABI class: XFree86 Server Extension, version 0.1
(II) Loading extension GLX
(II) Loading sub module "GLcore"
(II) LoadModule: "GLcore"
(II) Reloading /usr/X11R6/lib/modules/extensions/libGLcore.a
...</pre>
		<p>
          what you want to see here is something like:
		</p>
<pre>...
(II) LoadModule: "glx"
(II) Loading /usr/X11R6.4/lib/modules/extensions/libglx.so
(II) Module glx: vendor="NVIDIA Corporation"
	compiled for 4.0.1, module version = 1.0.5
	Module class: XFree86 Server Extension
	ABI class: XFree86 Server Extension, version 0.1
(II) Loading extension GLX
...</pre>
    		<p>the last part of Mesa that can cause problems is the actual OpenGL
    library, commonly called <path>libGL.so.1.2.303</path>... or similar. depending on
    where it is installed, it will conflict with nVidia's OpenGL library
    sooner or later. most games load <path>libGL.so</path> dynamically - they load it
    when they first start and reload it when loading a map or when applying
    new video settings. it happens quite often that a game loads the proper
    libGL.so the first time around and Mesa later on.
		</p>
		<p>
    symptoms of conflicts with Mesa (libraries and extensions) are crashes
    with Segmentation Faults (Signal 11) - either instantaneously after you
    start X or when you attempt to run an OpenGL application. another
    indication of such a conflict is extremely poor performance (1-5 fps),
    which happens when you get Mesa software rendering.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>nv_drv.o vs. nvidia_drv.o</title>
		<body><p>
       another common problem - after a default installation, XFree86's <c>nv</c>
       driver module will be loaded. you want to load <c>nvidia</c>. make sure
       your Device section in <path>XF86Config</path> looks somewhat like:
		</p>
<pre>Section "<i>Device</i>"
	Identifier  "<i>nVidia GeForce 256 DDR</i>"
	Driver      "<i>nvidia</i>"
EndSection</pre>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
    X Instantaneously Crashes With Signal 11
		</title>
		<body><p>
       check <path>/var/log/XFree86.0.log</path> for warnings like:
		</p>
		<pre>
       (WW) module ABI minor version (2) is newer than the server's version (1)
		</pre>
		<p>
       this commonly happens when you attempt to run 0.9-5 or later with
       XFree86 4.0.0 or 0.9-4 or earlier with XFree86 4.0.1 or later. i
       recommend you upgrade X to 4.0.2 and get whichever is the latest
       driver when you read this document.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>

    X Crashes Complaining about DMA
		</title>
		<body><p>
       probably an improper kernel - use 2.2.18+ or 2.4.0+.
		</p>
	</body></section>

	<section>
		<title>

    Monitor Looses Sync when staring X
		</title>
		<body><p>
       this can have various reasons:
       <ul>
		<li><p>you specified improper modelines - either delete any explicit
          modeline that may have been installed in your Monitor section or
          correct them.</p>
</li>
		<li>


       <p>the modelines are find, but the driver doesn't appear to like
          them - try these options in your Screen section:</p>
<pre>Option      "<i>IgnoreEdid</i>"       "<i>1</i>"
Option      "<i>GenerateRTList</i>"   "<i>0</i>"</pre>
		</li>
	</ul>
	</p>	</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>X &amp;&amp; MTRRs</title>
		<body><p>
       if you want support for MTRRs (you do), you'll have to enable support
       for them in the kernel itself before the driver will be able to use
       them. MTRRs greatly influence the speed of your setup.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>X Deletes Desired Modes (hsync out of range)</title>
		<body><p>
       X decided that your monitor is not capable of safely displaying the
       mode you asked it for. make sure the values you specified for
       HorizSync and VertRefresh match your monitor (look them up in your
       monitor's manual). if no values are specified, X will use rather
       conservative values.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>X Keeps Telling (Warning) You About a Polarity Option</title>
		<body><p>
       commonly happens when switching to console - usually harmless; if
       you don't know that X is talking about and want to get rid of the
       messages, use this in your Screen section:
		</p>
           <pre>Option      "<i>OverridePolarity</i>" "<i>1</i>"</pre>
		<p>
       This may speed up the console switches as well.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>DDC</title>
		<body><p>
       Yes, XFree86 4.0.x supports DDC - you can enable support for it by
       loading the appropriate module:
		</p>
           <pre>Load "<i>ddc</i>"</pre>
		<p>
       this will only work if both your video card and monitor support DDC.
       don't use explicit modelines alongside this option.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
    Game XY Doesn't Go Fullscreen
		</title>
		<body><p>
       this is a config problem. two prerequisites must be met before a game
       will be able to change resolutions using the X Vidmode Extenstion:
		</p>
		<p>

       you must have this line in XF86Config's Module Section:
		</p>
           <pre>Load "<i>extmod</i>"    <comment># or alternatively, a SubSection for <e>extmod</e></comment></pre>
		<p>
       you must have a proper <c>Display SubSection</c> in your <c>Screen</c> section - it
       must define the mode the game needs for the color depth you're
       running X at. e.g.:
		</p>
<pre>Subsection "<i>Display</i>"
	Depth  <i>24</i>
	Modes  "<i>1152x864</i>" "<i>1024x768</i>" "<i>800x600</i>" "<i>640x480</i>"
EndSubsection</pre>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>
     X Goes 16bpp, You Want 32, But That Doesn't Work
	</title>
		<body><p>
       24/32bpp in X 4.x is now labeled Depth 24. This is controlled by two
       options in your Screen Section:
		</p><pre>
           DefaultDepth <i>24</i>
           DefaultFbBpp <i>32</i>
		</pre>
		<p>
       again, make sure you have a proper Display Subsection.
		</p></body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Wheelmouse Doesn't Work</title>
		<body><p>
       Not nvidia related, but still asked quite often. you need to set
       the protocol to IMPS/2 and map the 4th and 5th button to the Z
       Axis. this is what my config looks like:
		</p><pre>
           Section "<i>InputDevice</i>"
             Identifier  "<i>Mouse</i>"
             Driver      "<i>mouse</i>"
             Option      "<i>Device</i>"  "<i>/dev/mouse</i>"
             Option      "<i>Protocol</i>"    "<i>IMPS/2</i>"
             Option      "<i>ZAxisMapping</i>"   "<i>4 5</i>"
           EndSection
		</pre><p>
       i'm using a USB mouse, <path>/dev/mouse</path> is a symling to <path>/dev/input/mice</path> in
       my case.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title> Mouse SUCKS In Games (QuakeIII, FPS XY)</title>
		<body><p>
       many games use DGA mouse for mouse input in games. this is similar
       to the directmouse thing in windows. all versions of XFree86 prior to
       4.0.2 had a somewhat broken DGA 1 mouse handling. If you want decent
       mouse performance upgrade to 4.0.2.
</p>
		<p>
       in addition to that, you'll have to load the DGA extension. many
       config tools disable that by default. use:
</p>
           <pre>Load "<i>extmod</i>"</pre>
		<p>
       instead of a SubSection if you want to make sure it gets loaded.
       after that, you'll have to enable DGA mouse in the game itself. for
       QuakeIII this comes down to
		</p>
           <pre>seta in_dgamouse "<i>1</i>"</pre>
		<p>
       in the QuakeIII config file (<path>~/.q3a/baseq3/q3config.cfg</path>).
		</p>
		<note>
       XFree86 4.0.2 introduce DGA 2, which is said to work even better.
       while QuakeIII doesn't support it yet, you can make pretty much all
       Loki games use it by compiling SDL with support for it.
		</note>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Application XY misses GLUT or GLU (glut.h / glu.h)</title>
		<body>
       <p>GLUT is a windowing toolkit that provides programmers with an easy
       way to setup windows with OpenGL contexts and allows some basic
       event handling (OpenGL knows nothing about that). It is not
       distributed as part of the nVidia driver. GLU is an utility library
       that sits on top of OpenGL. It is also not part of nVidia's driver
       distribution.
	</p>
	<p>
       Both GLUT and GLU can be obtained from the Mesa Project homepage and
       are likely to be available as packages from your Linux distribution.
	</p>
	<p>The following sections are Additions from <mail link="mthome@bbn.com">Michael Thome</mail></p>
	<ul><li>
      <p>Don't use the kernel nvidia FBdev driver, it conflicts with the
       proprietary NVIDIA drivers and causes all kinds of unpleasant
       effects (crashes, display problems, etc).</p>
	</li>
	<li>
      <p>Aureal's closed source Vortex drivers don't seem to come along
       with NVIDIA's binary drivers on some configuratins, possibly due
       to IRQ conflicts.</p>
	<warn>
          IRQ sharing seems to be a problem with NVIDIA's driver. I was
          unable to persuade a Fast Ethernet card (RTL8139) to work with 
          the driver under similar circumstances. If you have problems
          with hardware failing to operate properly or not at all, you
          may want to double-check that its not sharing its interrupt
          with your graphics adapter.
	</warn>
	</li>
	</ul>
	</body></section>
<section><title>100dpi mode
</title><body><p>
       Unlike the XFree86 driver, the NVIDIA module does not use DDC to
       figure out the screen resolution (dpi). I needed to add the
       following to my monitor section in order to get into 100dpi mode:
</p>

<pre>Section "<i>Monitor</i>"
	Identifier   "<i>Monitor0</i>"
	VendorName   "<i>Dell</i>"
	ModelName    "<i>Monitor Model</i>"
	HorizSync    <i>30.0-107.0</i>
	VertRefresh  <i>48.0-160.0</i>

	<comment># for 100dpi</comment>
	DisplaySize  <i>406 304</i>
EndSection</pre>
<p>
       The parameters are the monitor's displayable width and height
       in mm. I chose these values to result in 100x100dpi while in
       1600x1200 mode.
</p>
</body></section></chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Resources</title>
	<section>
		<title>
    My <path>/etc/X11/XF86Config</path> [0.9-6] for those who are interested:
</title><body>
<pre>    Section "<i>Module</i>"
      Load  "<i>bitmap</i>"
      Load  "<i>dbe</i>"
      Load  "<i>extmod</i>"
      Load  "<i>freetype</i>"
      Load  "<i>glx</i>"
      Load  "<i>type1</i>"
      Load  "<i>v4l</i>"
    EndSection

    Section "<i>Files</i>"
      RgbPath   "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/rgb</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/misc/</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi/:unscaled</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi/:unscaled</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi/</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi/</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/TrueType/</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/local/</i>"
      FontPath  "<i>/usr/X11R6.4/lib/X11/fonts/Type1/</i>"
    EndSection

    Section "<i>ServerFlags</i>"
      Option  "<i>SuspendTime</i>"  "<i>0</i>"
      Option  "<i>StandbyTime</i>"  "<i>0</i>"
      Option  "<i>BlankTime</i>"    "<i>0</i>"
      Option  "<i>OffTime</i>"      "<i>0</i>"
    EndSection

    Section "<i>InputDevice</i>"
      Identifier  "<i>Keyboard</i>"
      Driver      "<i>Keyboard</i>"
      Option      "<i>XkbRules</i>"  "<i>xfree86</i>"
      Option      "<i>XkbModel</i>"    "<i>pc102</i>"
      Option      "<i>XkbLayout</i>"      "<i>us</i>"
    EndSection

    Section "<i>InputDevice</i>"
      Identifier  "<i>Mouse</i>"
      Driver      "<i>mouse</i>"
      Option      "<i>Device</i>"  "<i>/dev/mouse</i>"
      Option      "<i>Protocol</i>"    "<i>IMPS/2</i>"
      Option      "<i>ZAxisMapping</i>"   "<i>4 5</i>"
      Option      "<i>Buttons</i>"          "<i>5</i>"
    EndSection

    Section "<i>Monitor</i>"
      Identifier  "<i>Vision Master Pro 17</i>"

      HorizSync    <i>27.0-92.0</i>
      VertRefresh  <i>50-160</i>

      Mode "<i>1152x864</i>"
        DotClock <i>137.65</i>
        HTimings <i>1152 1184 1312 1536</i>
        VTimings  <i>864  866  882  902</i>
        Flags    "<i>-HSync</i>" "<i>-VSync</i>"
      EndMode

      Mode "<i>1024x768</i>"
        DotClock <i>115.50</i>
        HTimings <i>1024 1056 1248 1440</i>
        VTimings  <i>768  771  781  802</i>
        Flags    "<i>-HSync</i>" "<i>-VSync</i>"
      EndMode

      Mode "<i>800x600</i>"
        DotClock <i>69.65</i>
        HTimings <i>800 864 928 1088</i>
        VTimings <i>600 604 610  640</i>
        Flags    "<i>-HSync</i>" "<i>-VSync</i>"
      EndMode

      Mode "<i>640x480</i>"
        DotClock <i>45.80</i>
        HTimings <i>640 672 768 864</i>
        VTimings <i>480 488 494 530</i>
        Flags    "<i>-HSync</i>" "<i>-VSync</i>"
      EndMode
    EndSection

    Section "<i>Device</i>"
      Identifier  "<i>nVidia GeForce 256 DDR</i>"
      Driver      "<i>nvidia</i>"
    EndSection

    Section "<i>Screen</i>"
      Identifier  "<i>Screen</i>"
      Device      "<i>nVidia GeForce 256 DDR</i>"
      Monitor     "<i>Vision Master Pro 17</i>"
      Option      "<i>NvAgp</i>" "<i>2</i>"

      DefaultDepth <i>24</i>
      DefaultFbBpp <i>32</i>

      Subsection "<i>Display</i>"
        Depth  <i>16</i>
        Modes  "<i>1152x864</i>" "<i>1024x768</i>" "<i>800x600</i>" "<i>640x480</i>"
      EndSubsection

      Subsection "<i>Display</i>"
        Depth  <i>24</i>
        Modes  "<i>1152x864</i>" "<i>1024x768</i>" "<i>800x600</i>" "<i>640x480</i>"
      EndSubsection
    EndSection

    Section "<i>ServerLayout</i>"
      Identifier   "<i>Chronos</i>"
      Screen       "<i>Screen</i>"
      InputDevice  "<i>Keyboard</i>" "<i>CoreKeyboard</i>"
      InputDevice  "<i>Mouse</i>"  "<i>CorePointer</i>"
    EndSection</pre>
</body>
</section>

<section>

<title>My host.def</title>
<body><p>
    For those who compile X themselves, this is my <path>host.def</path> that gets
    rid of some of the stuff you don't need anyway and adds some PPro 
    optimization (copy to <path>xc/config/cf</path>):
</p>
<pre>    #define DefaultCCOptions     <i>-O3 -march=i686 -Wall -ansi -pedantic</i>
    #define DefaultGcc2i386Opt   <i>-O3 -march=i686 -fno-strength-reduce</i>
    #define LibraryCDebugFlags   <i>-O3 -march=i686 -fno-strength-reduce</i>
    #define DefaultCDebugFlags   <i>-O3 -march=i686 -fno-strength-reduce</i>
    #define OptimizedCDebugFlags <i>-O3 -march=i686 -fno-strength-reduce</i>

    #define Freetype2Dir      <i>/usr/local</i>
    #define ProjectRoot     <i>/usr/X11R6.4</i>

    #define XF86CardDrivers       <i>nv v4l</i>
    #define XInputDrivers          <i>mouse</i>

    #define BuildServersOnly          <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildXF86DRI              <i>NO</i>
    #define XnestServer               <i>NO</i>
    #define XprtServer                <i>NO</i>
    #define XVirtualFramebufferServer <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildFontServer           <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildXinerama             <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildXF86RushExt          <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildPexExt               <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildGlxExt               <i>NO</i>
    #define LinuxFBDevSupport         <i>NO</i>
    #define XF1Bpp                    <i>NO</i>
    #define XF4Bpp                    <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildXTrueType            <i>NO</i>

    #define BuildSpeedo               <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildCID                  <i>NO</i>

    #define BuildCyrillicFonts        <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildSpeedoFonts          <i>NO</i>
    #define BuildCIDFonts             <i>NO</i>
    #define MakeLocalFontDir          <i>NO</i></pre>
</body>
</section>
</chapter></guide>
