<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide link="/doc/portage-user.html">
<title>Portage User Guide</title>
<author title="Chief Architect"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="thomasfl@gentoo.org">Thomas Flavel</mail></author>

<abstract>This guide briefly covers how to keep your packages up to date, and how to maintain
your system.</abstract>

<version>1.2.1</version>
<date>17 Oct 2001</date>

<chapter>
<title>Getting Started</title>

<section>
<title>Downloading the Portage tree</title>
<body>

<p>After you get Gentoo Linux installed and you play around a bit, you may find some bugs or
quirks in some packages, or maybe you'd like to install the latest Gentoo Linux software 
packages or update your current packages. To do this, you'll need to download our Portage
ports tree. We have provided an anonymous rsync server that you can use to get our latest
Portage tree. Here's how you use it.</p>

<p>First, make a directory called <path>/usr/portage</path>. Then, make sure rsync is installed. If it
isn't, download it from our ibiblio mirror and install it by typing <c>emerge
rsync-x.y.z.tbz2</c>. Then, use the following command to synchronize your Portage
directory:
</p>
<pre>
# <i>emerge rsync</i>
</pre>

<p>Periodically, you'll want to run this next form of the rsync command, which will delete
any old ebuild scripts:</p>

<warn>Please note that <c>emerge --clean rsync </c> will delete any of your
personal changes or additions to the <path>/usr/portage tree</path>, so use
this command with caution.</warn>

<pre>
# <i>emerge --clean rsync </i>
</pre>

<p>If you are making regular changes to your <path>/usr/portage</path> tree,
you may want to contact <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel</mail> for CVS
access so that you can commit some or all of them to our official Portage CVS tree.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Updating Portage</title>
<body>
<p>Before using our Portage tree, it's important that you update Portage. To do this, do the 
following:
</p>

<pre>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/sys-apps/portage</i>
# <i>emerge portage-x.y.z.ebuild</i>
</pre>

<p>Now you'll be using the most recent version of portage, and you can start to use our ebuild
system to update your installed software.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Introducing <c>emerge</c></title>
<section>
<title><c>emerge --pretend</c></title>
<body><p> 
To install a package, enter its directory in <path>/usr/portage</path>, i.e:
</p>

<pre>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/net-irc/xchat</i> 
</pre>

<p>Then, run <c>emerge --pretend</c> to see what dependencies (if any) will be installed:</p>

<pre>
# <i>emerge --pretend xchat-1.4.3.ebuild</i>

These are the packages that I would merge, in order.

Calculating dependencies......... done!
[ebuild   U] sys-libs/zlib-1.1.3-r2 to /
[ebuild   U] dev-libs/glib-1.2.10 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/jpeg-6b-r2 to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-base/xfree-4.0.3-r3 to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-libs/gtk+-1.2.10-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/giflib-4.1.0-r3 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/tiff-3.5.6_beta to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/imlib-1.9.10 to /
[ebuild N  ] net-irc/xchat-1.4.3 to /
</pre>

<p>In this particular case, we are attempting to merge <path>xchat</path> on a
machine that does not have X installed.  Thus, <c>emerge --pretend</c>
correctly identifies that several dependencies need to be satisfied first.
Specifically, <path>sys-libs/zlib</path> and <path>dev-libs/glib</path> need to
be updated, and then a bunch of ebuilds (including <path>x11-base/xfree</path>,
of course) need to be merged.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>USE and <c>emerge</c></title>
<body>
<p>Above, I executed <c>emerge --pretend</c> on a system that did not have
<c>gnome</c> defined in the <c>USE</c> variable in <path>/etc/make.conf</path>.
This means that optional GNOME support, if present, will not be enabled.
However, <path>xchat</path> <e>does</e> have optional GNOME support, so let's
take a look at the <c>emerge --pretend</c> output after I add <c>gnome</c> to
the <c>USE</c> environment variable in <path>/etc/make.conf</path>:
</p>

<pre>
# <i>emerge --pretend xchat-1.4.3.ebuild</i>

These are the packages that I would merge, in order.

Calculating dependencies............................ done!
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/jpeg-6b-r2 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/libghttp-1.0.9 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/audiofile-0.2.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-sound/esound-0.2.22-r2 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/gnome-env-1.0 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/libxml-1.8.11 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/ORBit-0.5.8 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/oaf-0.6.5 to /
[ebuild   U] dev-libs/glib-1.2.10 to /
[ebuild N  ] net-libs/libwww-5.3.2-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/giflib-4.1.0-r3 to /
[ebuild N  ] dev-util/guile-1.4-r3 to /
[ebuild   U] sys-libs/zlib-1.1.3-r2 to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-base/xfree-4.0.3-r3 to /
[ebuild N  ] x11-libs/gtk+-1.2.10-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/tiff-3.5.6_beta to /
[ebuild N  ] media-libs/imlib-1.9.10 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/gnome-libs-1.2.13 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/glibwww-0.2-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/gdk-pixbuf-0.11.0 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/gconf-1.0.0 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/gnome-vfs-1.0.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/control-center-1.4.0.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/scrollkeeper-0.2 to /
[ebuild N  ] dev-util/xml-i18n-tools-0.8.1 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/libglade-0.16-r1 to /
[ebuild N  ] gnome-base/gnome-core-1.4.0.4 to /
[ebuild N  ] net-irc/xchat-1.4.3 to /
</pre>

<p>As you can see, with <c>gnome</c> added to <c>USE</c>, emerge recognizes
that xchat should include optional GNOME support.  And of course, in order for
this optional GNOME support to compile and run correctly, GNOME must first be
installed.  <c>emerge</c> figures this all out and adds various packages
required by GNOME to its list of ebuilds to merge.  There may be times where
your <c>USE</c> variable is not set correctly, causing <c>emerge</c> to
unexpectedly include or exclude support for various optional extensions.
That's why I recommended that you always perform an <c>emerge --pretend</c>
before executing the actual <c>emerge</c>, especially for new, unfamiliar
ebuilds.  That way, you'll know what to expect. :)  Once everything looks OK,
you can go ahead with the actual <c>emerge</c> by dropping the <c>--pretend</c>
option:</p>

<pre>
# <i>emerge xchat-1.4.3.ebuild</i>
</pre>

<p>After all dependencies are merged (if they exist; not all packages have
them), the xchat sources will be downloaded (to
<path>/usr/portage/distfiles</path>), verified, unpacked, compiled and
installed to a temporary directory. Then, they will be merged into the local
filesystem and a package database will be created at
<path>/var/db/pkg/net-irc/xchat-1.4.3/CONTENTS</path>, containing the files
installed and the md5sums for all files.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Upgrading packages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>The standard way to upgrade packages under Gentoo Linux is to merge the new package,
and then unmerge the old package. This is safe (and fun!) to do. First, merge the new package
as per the above instructions. Then, uninstall the old package by typing something
like:</p>

<pre>
# <i>ebuild /var/db/pkg/net-irc/xchat-1.0.0-r1/xchat-1.0.0-r1.ebuild unmerge</i>
</pre>

<p>For now, unmerging is performed using the lower-level <c>ebuild</c> command, rather
than <c>emerge</c>.  This will likely change in the near future as we begin moving more
and more functionality over to the high-level <c>emerge</c> tool.
</p>

<p>When using <c>ebuild</c>, it's important to specify the exact path to the ebuild
file in <path>/var/db/pkg</path> that you'd like to unmerge.  
Portage uses what is called a "safe" unmerge; it's only going to
unlink original files. If a file has been overwritten or modified in some way,
it will be left on the filesystem (presumably, you've installed a newer version
of the package). So, if you unmerge an old version of xchat after merging a
newer version, the xchat executable will not be deleted off your filesystem,
since it has a newer timestamp and different md5sum. Safe unmerges are really
great because they ensure that some version of the application is available at
all times. If you had to unmerge first, then xchat wouldn't be available
for a few minutes while the new version was being downloaded, compiled,
installed and merged.</p>

<impo>Portage now has a special feature called "config file protection".  The purpose of
this feature is to prevent new package installs from clobbering existig
configuration files.  By default, config file protection is turned on for /etc
and the KDE configuration dirs; more may be added in the future.  Type 
<c>emerge --help config</c> for more details.</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
