<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide type="project" link="/projects/xml.html">
<title>XML projects page</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<abstract>
This page contains information about the "guide" XML project, used for the
Gentoo Linux documentation and Web site.
</abstract>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>02 Sep 2001</date>

<chapter>
<title>Guide XML</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>The Gentoo Linux team uses a special simple XML format called <c>guide
XML</c> for all of its documentation and web pages.  If you're interested in
learning more about this format, you may want to read the <e>A site reborn</e>
series of <uri link="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks">IBM
developerWorks</uri> articles, written by Daniel Robbins:</p>

<ul>
	<li>In <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/usability/library/us-gentoo/index.html">Part 1</uri>, Daniel creates a user-centric action plan and introduces <c>pytext</c>, an embedded Python interpreter.</li>
	<li>In <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/usability/library/us-gent/">Part 2</uri>, Daniel shows off the new <c>guide XML</c> documentation system and sets up a daily CVS-log mailing list.</li>
	<li>In <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/usability/library/us-gentoo3/">Part 3</uri>, Daniel designs a new look for the site as a whole.</li>
	<li>In <uri link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/usability/library/us-gentoo4/">Part 4</uri>, Daniel completes the conversion to XML/XSLT, fixes a host of Netscape 4.x browser compatibility bugs, and adds an auto-generated XML Changelog to the site.</li>
</ul>

<p>We also have a <uri link="/doc/xml-guide.html">Gentoo Linux Documentation
Guide</uri> that explains how to use the <c>guide XML</c> format.  You can
download the latest version of all our <c>guide XML</c> tools by grabbing this file, which actually contains a CVS snapshot of all the files used to create the website: <uri
link="/projects/guide-xml-latest.tar.gz">xml-guide-latest.tar.gz</uri>.  This
tarball is automatically regenerated every time the Gentoo Linux Web site
is updated, so it will always be current.  Instructions on how to use the
included files can be found in the <uri link="/doc/xml-guide.html">Gentoo Linux Documentation Guide</uri> (FYI, this
tarball contains a snapshot of the <path>/usr/portage/app-doc/gentoo-web/files</path> directory).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>

