<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
<herd>gnustep</herd>
<longdescription>
StepTalk is the official GNUstep scripting framework. StepTalk is more than a scripting framework with an illusion of single objective environment between objects of scriptable servers or applications. StepTalk, when combined with the dynamism that the Objective-C language provides, goes way beyond mere scripting. It is language independent - it uses languages as separate bundles.

Introduction
------------
The default scripting language in StepTalk is Smalltalk. This is because Smalltalk is a very simple language and it is easy to learn. There are just a few basic principles that the user has to know to be able to use the language and it is close to the natural language.

Smalltalk uses a similar approach to that of Objective-C, the language used in GNUstep itself.

Other Scripting Languages
-------------------------
StepTalk is a language independent framework. It can be extended by the "language bundles" providing other scripting languages. One experimental language bundle for Guile is included in the sources package.

Object Finders
--------------
...an illusion of single objective environment. Name of an object may me known, but the object itself not. The object may be an application or it may reside on other host. Object Finder is an object that will search for object by specified name.

* Distributed Object Finder - This finder will try to look for a registered named object. It is possible to specify list of possible hosts where the object may reside and to specify a program that will provide the object if it cannot be found.
* Application Finder - Looks for a locally installed application and tries to connect to it. If the application is not running, it will try to launch it.

The Framework
-------------
* multiple languages
* object finders
* scripting environments
* restrictions for object's methods
* dynamic module loading

Tools
-----
stexec - execute scripts in GNUstep environment
stalk - tool for talking to the GNUstep servers and applications
</longdescription>
<use>
	<flag name='gdl2'>Compile module for <pkg>gnustep-libs/gdl2</pkg></flag>
</use>
</pkgmetadata>
